Finding Aid for School of Natural Resources and Environment (University of Michigan) Publications 1903-2011
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
School of Natural Resources and Environment (University of Michigan) publications 1903-2011
University of Michigan. School of Natural Resources and Environment.
Includes annual reports, bibliographies, brochures, bulletins or college catalogs, directories, histories, manuals, newsletters, programs, reports, and surveys. Also contains annual reports, brochures, directories, histories, manuals, newsletters and reports from the Biological Station, Michigan Sea Grant Program, and the Wildland Management Center; as well as newsletters from the Dept. of Forestry and Dept. of Wood Technology and manuals and proposals from ENACT (Environmental Action for Survival). In addition there are by-laws, newsletters, programs, and the yearbooks entitled "Michigan Forester" from the Forestry Club, the Foresters Club, and the Foresters Association. There are also several editions of alumni directories, as well as student publications.
9734 Bimu C241 2
7.5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
Publications are received periodically from the unit (Donor no. 1887 )
The publications are open to research.
The School of Natural Resources (SNR) was established in 1927 but forestry courses had been offered at the University of Michigan as early as 1881. It was the first university in the United States to offer regular course work in forestry. The first forestry course was given in 1881 by Professor Morgan Volney Spalding in the School of Political Science. This forestry offering lapsed after four years, however.
In 1901, at the instigation of Spalding and Charles W. Garfield of Grand Rapids, the Board of Regents voted to renew the forestry program. Charles Albert Davis was appointed special instructor in forestry and courses were offered in 1902. The following year a separate Forestry Department, headed by Filibert Roth, was created in the College of Literature, Science and the Arts (LS&A). The department offered a combined undergraduate and graduate program that included four years of the usual course work for the B.A. with forestry electives, and one year of graduate study.
Under Roth's direction the curriculum and the faculty expanded to keep pace with developments in the forestry profession. The University of Michigan became one of the best known forestry schools. Professor Roth retired in 1923. The naming of a successor was delayed as University President Burton used the occasion of Roth's retirement to undertake a reevaluation of the forestry program.
In 1926 the Regents voted approval for an expanded forestry program. This led to the creation of an independent School of Forestry and Conservation in 1927. Samuel Trask Dana was named the school's first dean. Dana immediately began to recruit new faculty and develop a more comprehensive curriculum. Enrollment, which had declined due to the uncertainty following Roth's retirement and the impact of the depression, began to grow steadily after 1931. Spurred by the work of the Civilian Conservation Corps and other government conservation activity, enrollment reached 187 full-time students in 1939/40. With the onset of World War II, the number of students dropped precipitously only to be followed by a postwar boom in enrollment.
In 1949 a committee of four noted conservationists was engaged to consider a reorganization of the school in light of developments in the forestry and conservation professions. The committee report was received favorably, but Dean Dana had prepared his own more sweeping proposal for reorganization. His plan called for creation of an expanded School of Natural Resources which would offer degrees in regional planning and general conservation in addition to the traditional training programs in forestry, wood technology, wildlife management, and fisheries management.
The School of Natural Resources originally had been organized into five departments: Forestry, Wood Technology, Fisheries Management, Wildlife Management, and Conservation. The first three departments were carried over from the old Department of Forestry. Fisheries Management had been located in the Zoology Department of LS&A. As its work had become more applied, it was deemed appropriate to shift the fisheries program to the School of Natural Resources.
The Conservation Department developed from a $100,000 grant from the Charles Lathrop Pack Foundation for the purpose of training students in the entire field of conservation. Noted ecologist Stanley A. Cain was named the first Pack Professor of Conservation in 1950. The Conservation Department offered a number of interdisciplinary programs including natural resources economics with the Economics Department and environmental planning and water resources with the School of Public Health. By the mid-1960s conservation had become the largest SNR department. To better reflect its expanded curriculum, the Conservation Department's name was changed to Resource Planning and Conservation in 1969.
While the Conservation Department was growing, other departments experienced little or no growth, prompting some significant reorganization of the school. The Wood Technology Department was phased out in 1964 and its faculty transferred to Forestry. In 1965 the Fisheries and Wildlife Management Departments were administratively combined but separate curriculums were maintained.
Also in 1965, SNR acquired a new department with the transfer of Landscape Architecture from the College of Architecture and Design. During this period SNR instituted a naturalist curriculum and expanded its offerings in forest recreation. The latter development resulted in the endowing of the Samuel T. Dana Professorship of Outdoor Recreation.
The School of Natural Resources has also been host to several interdepartmental projects. These include the Remote Sensing of the Environment Program, the Environmental Simulation Laboratory, and the Sea Grant Program.
In 1970 the university undertook a broad review of its programs relating to environmental education and the management and development of natural resources. A university-wide committee headed by Vice President Stephen Spurr recommended that the university establish a College of Environmental Studies of which SNR would be a part. The College of Environmental Studies was not established but SNR did revise its structure and curriculum along the lines recommended by the Spurr committee. The existing SNR departments were abolished and programs were to be offered in six areas: Systems Management; Fisheries, Forestry, and Wildlife; Resource Ecology; Resource Policy and Administration; Environmental Education; and Landscape Architecture.
Over the years SNR has acquired or managed several forest properties for educational and scientific purposes. These have included the Eberwhite Woods in west Ann Arbor, the Saginaw Forest property further west of Ann Arbor on Liberty Road, the Stinchfield Woods property near Dexter, the Ringwood tract near Saginaw, and Camp Filibert Roth in Iron County.
As noted above, Samuel Trask Dana was named the first dean of SNR in 1927. He guided the school for twenty-three years until his retirement in 1950. He remained an active presence in the school as emeritus dean. Dana selected his own successor, Stanley G. Fontanna. Formerly deputy director of the State of Michigan Department of Conservation, Fontanna held the deanship from 1951 to 1962. He was succeeded by Stephen H. Spurr, professor of silviculture. Spurr served through 1965 when he was appointed dean of the university's Horace H. Rackham School of Graduate Studies.
Kenneth P. Davis, professor of forest management, was appointed interim dean for 1965/66. Dr. Keith Arnold of the U.S. Forest Service served as dean for three years, 1967-1969. Arnold was succeeded by James T. McFadden, chairman of the school's Department of Fisheries and Wildlife Management. McFadden was the first non-forester to be named dean and served as dean until 1974.
William J. Johnson, chairman of the school's Landscape Architecture program, was selected to succeed McFadden. When Johnson stepped down as dean in 1983 to return to academics, he was succeeded by James E. Crowfoot. Confronted with budget reductions and a review by the University of Michigan, Crowfoot provided SNR with the necessary leadership during an intense period of scrutiny. Crowfoot stepped down as dean in December 1990 to chair the Resource, Policy and Behavior concentration and left the University of Michigan in 1994 to assume the presidency of Antioch College. In addition to his responsibilities as dean, Crowfoot was co-founder of the Program in Conflict Management Alternatives. An advocate of the democratic management of organizations, he developed a new curriculum emphasis in environmental dispute resolution.
Following Crowfoot's resignation Harrison Morton was appointed interim dean of the school until the appointment of Garry D. Brewer in 1992. Among Brewer's first achievements was implementing a name change for the School of Natural Resources. During the July 1992 meeting the University of Michigan Board of Regents approved a name change to the School of Natural Resources and Environment (SNRE). The name changes was designed to reflect the expanding scope of the school. Brewer left the deanship in 1995 and Paul Webb was appointed interim dean. Daniel A. Mazmanian, was appointed dean in June 1996.
Leadership of the School of Natural Resources and Environment and its Predecessors
Chairman of the Department of Forestry
1903-1923 Filibert Roth
1923-1927 Leigh J. Young (acting)
1927 Robert Craig, Jr. (acting)
Dean of the School of Forestry and Conservation
1927-1950 Samuel Trask Dana
Deans of the School of Natural Resources
1950/1951 Samuel Trask Dana
1951-1962 Stanley George Fontanna
1962-1965 Stephen H. Spurr
1965-1966 Kenneth Davis (Interim)
1967-1969 Keith Arnold
1970-1974 James T. McFadden
1974-1975 Charles Olson (Interim)
1975-1983 William J. Johnson
1983-1990 James Crowfoot
1991-1992 Harrison Morton (Interim)
School of Natural Resources and Environment
1992-1995 Garry D. Brewer
1995 Paul Webb (Interim)
1996-2000 Daniel A. Mazmanian
2000-2001 Barry Rabe (Interim)
2001- Rosina M. Bierbaum
The Publications of the School of Natural Resources and Environment are divided into four series: Unit Publications, Sub-Unit Publications, Topical Publications and Student Publications. Some publications (or their successors) may no longer be available in print but are available on the school s website.
Subjects:
University of Michigan--Alumni and alumnae.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs.; University of Michigan. School of Natural Resources and Environment.; University of Michigan. School of Natural Resources.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Forestry.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Wood Technology.; University of Michigan. Biological Station.; Michigan Sea Grant Program.; University of Michigan. Foresters Club.; University of Michigan. Foresters Association.; University of Michigan. Wildland Management Center.
Contributors:
University of Michigan. School of Natural Resources.; University of Michigan. Biological Station.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Forestry.; University of Michigan. Wildland Management Center.; Michigan Sea Grant Program.
Publications:
Michigan forester.
Genre/Form:
Annual reports.; Bibliographies.; Catalogs, College.; Directories.; Histories.; Manuals.; Newsletters.2aat.; Programs.; Reports.; Student publications.
- Unit Publications
  Unit Publications include bulletins, directories, and several newsletters, among which are News, whose title changed to Natural Resource News in 1987 and SNRE News in 1995. A college history will also be found here.
  - Addresses
    - Commencement Address 1987 (Box 1)
    - Forestry, Economic Stability and Unemployment Relief, 1932/33 (Box 1)
  - Annual Reports 1984/85-1991/92, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Bibliographies
    - Forest Photogrammetry and Aerial Mapping: A Bibliography, 1887-1955 (Box 1)
  - Booklets
    - Landscape Architecture Program Centennial Celebration 2009 (Box 1)
  - Brochures
    - Biological Sciences 1952-1978 (Box 1)
    - Conservation 1953-1957 (Box 1)
    - Conservation Biology and Ecosystem Management undated (Box 1)
    - Corporate Environmental Management Program undated (Box 1)
    - Course Offerings 1976-1999 (Box 1)
    - DANA Building Renovation 1999 (Box 1)
    - Doctoral Programs undated (Box 1)
    - Environmental undated, 1995 (Box 1)
    - Environmental Justice undated (Box 1)
    - Faculty Research Profile 1988-1990 (Box 1)
    - Fisheries undated, 1953-1957 (Box 1)
    - Forestry undated, 1953-1967 (Box 1)
    - Graduate Specialization in Environmental Justice undated (Box 1)
    - International Studies undated (Box 1)
    - Interpretive Walks 1990 (Box 1)
    - Landscape Architecture undated, 1994-1995 (Box 1)
    - Management, Planning and Policy undated (Box 1)
    - Masters Program undated (Box 1)
    - Masters Student Projects 1996-2001 (Box 1)
    - Minority Issues undated (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous undated, 1942-1995 (Box 1)
    - Natural Resource and Environmental Professionals, undated (Box 1)
    - Natural Resources undated (Box 1)
    - Outdoor Recreation undated (Box 1)
    - Regional Planning undated (Box 1)
    - Remote Sensing undated (Box 1)
    - Resource Ecology undated, 1995 (Box 1)
    - Resource Economics undated (Box 1)
    - Resource Policy and Behavior undated (Box 1)
    - Resource Policy and Management undated, 1995 (Box 1)
    - Training Leaders for the Furniture Industry at the University of Michigan, 1945-1947 (Box 1)
    - Undergraduate Program undated (Box 1)
    - Wildlife undated (Box 1)
    - Wood Technology 1953-1955 (Box 1)
  - Bulletins
    - 1903/04-1961/62, 11 folders (Box 1)
    - 1962/63-1991, 5 folders (Box 2)
    - Program degree requirements, 1988-2004/2005 (Box 2)
  - Directories
    - 1980-1982 (Box 2)
    - Black Landscape Architects and Black Landscape Architecture Students, 1990 (Box 2)
    - Employment Profiles of Selected Recent Graduates, undated (Box 2)
    - State Directory: University of Michigan Foresters, 1927 (Box 2)
  - Flyers and Announcements 2002-2011, undated (Box 2)
  - Histories
    - History of Activities in the Field of Natural Resources, 1953 (Box 2)
    - History of Activities in the Field of Natural Resources, the University of Michigan: Supplement Covering the Period 1953-1961 1962 (Box 2)
    - History of Activities in the Field of Natural Resources, the University of Michigan: Supplement Covering the Period 1962-1987, 1989 (Box 2)
  - Manuals
    - After Arrival it's a Case of Survival: A Student's Guide to the School of Natural Resources, undated (Box 2)
    - ASTSWMO (Association of State and Territorial Solid Waste Management Officials) Inspector Training Manual, 1987 (Box 2)
    - A Guide to Saginaw Forest, undated (Box 2)
    - A Guide to Stinchfield Woods, undated (Box 2)
    - Job Hunting: There's No Magic Method..., undated (Box 2)
    - The Spruce Budworm Handbook: A Management Guide for Spruce-Fir Stands in the Lake States, 1982 (Box 2)
    - Spruce-Fir Silviculture and the Spruce Budworm in the Lake States, 1983 (Box 2)
    - Zoo Design: The Reality of Wild Illusions 1987 (Box 2)
  - Newsletters
    - Ann Arbor Conservation Notes
      - 1940-1954 no. [1]-6 (Box 2)
    - Endangered Species Update 1997-2007, 5 folders (Box 2)
    - Equinox: Environmental Education and Outdoor Recreation Alumni Newsletter
      - 1979 v. 4 (Box 3)
    - Michiganscapes, 1991-2001 (Box 3)
    - Natural Resource News
      - 1987-1991 no. 37-42, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - News
      - 1978-1986 no. 1-36, 5 folders (Box 3)
    - News Notes, 1928 (Box 3)
    - The Resource, 1978 (Box 3)
    - SNR&E EE News, 2002 (Box 3)
    - SNR&E News, 1995 (Box 3)
    - SNRE News, 2002-2005 (Box 3)
    - Stewards, 2007-2009 (Box 3)
  - Posters 1982, undated (Box 3)
  - Proceedings
    - Planning-Budget Conference 1985 (Box 3)
  - Programs (Box 3)
  - Programs (cont.)
    - Administration of National Parks and Equivalent Preserves 1965-1987 (Box 3)
    - Celebration in Honor of Terry J. and Janice A. Brown 2006 (Box 3)
    - Colonel Ernest A.H. Woodman Memorial Service 1995 (Box 3)
    - Honors Convocation 1981-1989 (Box 3)
    - The PEW Fellows Program 1996 (Box 3)
    - Spring Commencement
      - 1987-1989 (Box 3)
      - 2003-2006 (Box 3)
    - University Convocation 1938-1953 (Box 3)
  - Reports
    - Building Trust: Lessons from Collaborative Planning on State Trust Lands, 2006 (Box 3)
    - Bulletin
      - 1932-1949 no. 1-12, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Circular
      - 1937-1942 no. 1-6 (Box 4)
    - Contribution
      - 1928-1934 no. 1-38, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Dean Search: Background Information 1991 (Box 4)
    - Exploring Rural Character and Environmental Quality in Green Oak Township, Michigan, circa late 1990s (Box 4)
    - Faculty Research and Teaching Interests 1986 (Box 4)
    - Glimpses of Saginaw Forest, Eber White Woods, Stinchfield Forest, 1946 (Box 4)
    - Landscape Architecture: Self-Evaluation Report, 1987/88 (Box 4)
    - Rampart Dam and the Economic Development of Alaska, 1966 (Box 4)
    - Recruitment Strategy 1985 (Box 4)
    - Red Pine Plantation Management in the Lake States: A Review, 1984 (Box 4)
    - Regional Landscape Ecosystems of Michigan, 1986 (Box 4)
    - School Evaluation Report: School of Natural Resources Landscape Architecture Program, 1981-1982 (Box 4)
    - Toward a Sustainable Future: Research at the School of Natural Resources, 1985 (Box 4)
    - The Value of Time in Environmental Decision Processes, vol. II 1979 (Box 4)
  - Schedules
    - Summer Session Program of Special Lectures, Excursions and Entertainments, 1913 (Box 4)
  - Surveys
    - School of Natural Resources Placement Survey undated (Box 4)
- Sub-Unit Publications
  Sub-Unit Publications consist of materials produced by units within the School of Natural Resources. These include the Alumni Society, the Association of Michigan Foresters, Biological Station, the Center for Strategic Wildlife Management, the Departments of Conservation, Fisheries, Forestry, Wildlife Management and Wood Technology, ENACT (Environmental Action for Survival), Environmental Education Program, Foresters Association, The Forestry Club (whose name changes to the Foresters Club), the International Seminar on Forest Administration and Management, the Meeman Archive, Natural Resource Sociology Lab, Project for the Study of Natural Resources and Environmental Conflict, the Student Policy Advisory Committee, Urban and Regional Planning Ph.D. Program and the Wildland Management Center. The publication Michigan Forester, which was first produced by the Forestry Club and later the Foresters Club, began as a newsletter and gradually evolved into the yearbook of the School of Natural Resources. This publication was replaced by The Source.
  - Alumni Society
    - Newsletters
      - Alumni Newsletter, 1966-1970 (Box 4)
  - Association of Michigan Foresters
    - Newsletters 1925-1927 (Box 4)
  - Biological Station (Box 4)
  - Biological Station (cont.)
    - Bibliographies
      - Bibliography of Papers, 1909-1945 (Box 4)
      - Bibliography of Research, 1958-1994 (Box 4)
      - Research Directories, 1932-1984 (Box 4)
    - Brochures
      - Miscellaneous undated, 1970-1989 (Box 4)
    - Bulletins
      - 1909-1993, 1995-2009, 15 folders (Box 4)
    - Histories
      - The University of Michigan Biological Station 1909-1983, 1983 (Box 4)
    - Manuals
      - Biological Station Guide, undated, 1969 (Box 4)
    - Newsletters
      - The Alumbs, 1984-1990 (Box 4)
      - Douglas Lake Report, 1975-1992, 2001 (scattered issues) (Box 4)
      - Lakeland Report, 1974-1976 no. 1-8 (Box 4)
      - UMBS News 1993 (Box 4)
    - Posters undated (Box 4)
    - Proceedings
      - Semicentennial Celebration Proceedings of the Biological Station, 1959 (Box 4)
    - Reports
      - Inland Lake Protection in Northern Michigan, 1975 (Box 4)
      - The Natural Ecology and Cultural History of the Colonial Point Red Oak Stands (Technical Report No. 14), 1987 (Box 4)
      - Northern Michigan Environmental Research Program, [1972] (Box 4)
      - Report of the Conference on the Upper Great Lakes, 1953 (Box 4)
      - Report of the Director of the Biological Station 1912-1924, 4 folders (Box 4)
  - Center for Strategic Wildlife Management Studies
    - Brochures
      - The Earth's Living Resources: Conservation for Sustainable Development, 1982 (Box 5)
  - Center for Sustainable Systems
    - Brochures
      - Factsheets 2005 (Box 5)
      - General undated (Box 5)
  - Department of Conservation
    - Newsletter 1962-1964 (Box 5)
    - Reports
      - Megalopolis Formation in the Midwest, 1965 (Box 5)
      - The Redeployment of Land, Water and Human Resources, 1962 (Box 5)
      - The First Three Years 1950-1953, 1953 (Box 5)
  - Department of Fisheries
    - Newsletters
      - Michigan Fisheries, 1957-1979 no. 1-13 (Box 5)
  - Department of Forestry
    - Newsletters
      - Michigan Forestry, 1953-1959 no. 1-22 (Box 5)
  - Department of Wildlife Management
    - Newsletters
      - Michigan Wildlife, 1955 no. 1-2 (Box 5)
  - Department of Wood Technology
    - Brochures
      - Activities and Facilities of the Department of Wood Technology, undated (Box 5)
    - Newsletters
      - Michigan Wood Technology, 1954-1962 no. 1-17 (Box 5)
  - ENACT (Environmental Action for Survival)
    - Catalogs
      - Films on the Environmental Crisis undated (Box 5)
    - Manuals
      - Guidelines for Citizen Action on Environmental Problems 1971 (Box 5)
    - Proposals
      - ...Is ENACT to Survive?, 1972 (Box 5)
    - Teach-In on the Environment 1970 (Box 5)
  - Environmental Education Program (Box 6)
    - Manuals
      - Writing About Wildlife: A Communications Textbook for Natural Resources Students, 1974 (Box 6)
  - Environmental Education and Training Program
    - Proposals
      - Proposal for the Environmental Education Training Program 1992 (Box 6)
  - Erb Institute
    - Brochures
      - Corporate Environmental Management Program undated (Box 6)
      - General undated (Box 6)
  - Foresters Association
    - By-Laws
      - By-Laws: University of Michigan Forester's Association, undated (Box 6)
    - Newsletters
      - 1928-1938, 4 folders (Box 6)
      - Forester's Association, 1939-1944, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Newsletter
        - 1950-1958 no. 55-70, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Programs
      - Reunion Programs 1928-1938 (Box 6)
  - Foresters Club
    - Programs
      - Paul Bunyan Ball 1968-1969 (Box 6)
    - Yearbooks
      - Michigan Forester
        - 1949-1966 v. 34-47, 10 folders (Box 6)
      - Source: Yearbook of the School of Natural Resources, 1968 (Box 7)
  - Forestry Club
    - Newsletters
      - Michigan Forester, 1910-1940 v. 1-21, 9 folders (Box 7)
    - Yearbooks
      - Michigan Forester, 1941-1948 v. 22-29, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Programs
      - Banquet in Honor of Professor Filibert Roth 1923 (Box 7)
  - The Global Rivers Environmental Education Network (GREEN)
    - Newsletters
      - GREEN, 1989-1990 (Box 7)
  - Institute for the Integrated Study of Global Change
    - Brochures 1995, undated (Box 7)
  - International Seminar on Forest Administration and Management
    - Brochures undated (Box 7)
    - Newsletters
      - Newsletter, 1990 v. 3 (Box 7)
    - Programs
      - International Seminar on Forest Administration and Management 1984-1990 (Box 7)
  - The Meeman Archive
    - Brochures
      - Miscellaneous undated (Box 7)
    - Catalogs
      - Environmental Journalism: The Best from the Meeman Archive, 1987 (Box 7)
    - Newsletters
      - The Meeman Archive Newsletter, v. 1, 1987/88 (Box 7)